你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到Pwn学院
welcome back to Pwn College
今天我们要讨论的是
today we're talking about
进程和线程
processes and threads
这当然是在竞态条件的背景下
this is of course in the context of race conditions
但在你整个计算机科学之旅中都是非常有用的
but the general information is quite useful in your journey of computer science
让我们来谈谈多线程
let's talk about multi-threads
但先从进程开始
but let's start with processes
到目前为止，在这门课上我们讨论了进程
so far in this class we talked about processes
目前一直接触的都是进程
a process is what you've been dealing with this whole time
当你启动一个程序时
when you start up a program
when you launch a program
它作为一个进程被加载到内存中
it gets loaded to memory as a process
并被执行
and gets executed
进程有自己的虚拟内存
processes have their own virtual memory
它有栈，堆，代码段，各种各样的东西
this has the stack the heap the binary all sorts of good stuff
有自己的寄存器
has its own registers
它有自己的文件描述符和进程ID
it has its own file descriptors a process ID
还有各种安全属性
and then various security properties
如uid gid seccomp规则等
uid gid seccomp rules
到目前为止，这些都接触过了
and you've messed around with all of these things so far in the course
但这还不是它真正的样子
well this isn't the reality actually
实际上，进程是由一个或多个线程组成的
the reality is that processes are made up of one or more threads
进程内的线程共享虚拟内存和文件描述符等等
and the threads within a process share the virtual memory and file descriptors and so forth
但他们都有自己的寄存器
but they all have their own registers
或者更确切地说，当他们被调度到后，有独自的寄存器上下文
or rather their own register context when they run get scheduled on a CPU to run
他们有自己的寄存器上下文，不与其他线程共享
they have their own registers that they don't share with other threads
他们有自己的栈
they have their own stack
如果有需要，他们也可以访问彼此的栈
now they can access each other stacks if they were crazy and doing that for some reason
因为他们都在同一个虚拟内存中
because they're all in the same virtual memory
但是他们在虚拟内存中的地址不同
but they are in different places in the virtual memory
他们有自己的线程ID
they have their own thread ID
主线程的线程ID和进程ID(PID)相同
the main thread has the same thread ID as the process ID the PID of the process
但是其他线程都有自己的线程id和
but the other threads all have their own thread ids and
他们有自己的安全属性
actually they have their own security properties
实际上每个线程都有自己的uid、gid 和 secomp 规则
their user ID their group ID Secomp rules are actually per thread
这很不可思议
which is pretty incredible
当你开启一个进程
and when you start a process
当然它有自己的主线程
of course it has its main thread
然后当你在这个进程中启动其他线程
and then as you spin up other threads in that process
进程将具有多种类型的线程
the process will have multiple kind of sibling threads
好的
all right
我们如何创建线程
how do we create threads
有几个不同的高级库
well there are several different high level libraries that
你可以用来创建线程
you should probably use if you want to create a thread
一个例子是pthread，它实际上非常简单
an example is pthread it's actually very simple
调用pthread_create
you call pthread_create
给它一个地址来存储返回的线程结构
give it somewhere to store a resulting thread structure
然后给它一个要运行的函数
and give it a function to run
和所需的参数
and an argument to run it with
超级简单，几乎和函数调用一样简单
super simple almost as simple as a function call
在新线程中使用所提供参数调用你提供的函数
it basically runs that function with argument you provide in a new thread
这个程序将创建两个线程
so this program will create two threads
每个线程将打印其详细信息
each thread will print out its details
主线程将打印出它的详细信息
the main thread will print out its details
然后它会执行pthread_join
and then it will do pthread_join
它等待这个线程执行结束
well this simply just waits for this thread to terminate
this waits for this thread to terminate
一切都很好
and everything is good
记住这些是独立的线程
now keep in mind these are individual threads
他们类似轻量级进程
they are kind of like processes light in reality
轻量级进程是共享一堆信息的进程
they are basically processes that share a bunch of information
我们马上就会讲到
as we'll talk about in a second
让我们快速看一下
so let's take a quick look
在这里我实现了这个程序
here I implemented that program
哦哦，等等技术问题
oh oh hold on technical issues
好了，我们回来
all right we are back
这里我们有一个线程
so here we have the thread
这个线程实现
that thread implementation basically
创建两个子线程
creating two child threads
当然，除此之外还有主线程
and then of course we have our main thread
编译它
let's compile it
当然，要编译它，我们需要将它链接pthread库
of course to compile it we need to link it against the pthread library
这不是，额，是一个标准库，但不是libc库
this is a non or it is a standard library but it's not libc
所以它不会自动链接进去
so it's not automatically linked in
当然，通常会有一堆警告
of course there's usual a bunch of warnings
如果我们运行
if we run
我们启动两个线程
we spin up two threads
主线程打印它的信息
and then the main thread prints out its information
每个线程都打印自己的信息
and each thread prints out its information
现在来看看
now check it out
我们先启动了线程1
we spun up thread 1 first
然后我们启动线程2
and then we spun up thread 2
但是线程2先被打印
but in our printout thread 2 gets printed first
线程1第二个被打印
and thread 1 gets printed second
实际上，如果你多运行几次
actually if you run this several times
会有很多不同的结果
there will be lots of different configurations
这里，线程1在主线程之前打印
so here thread 1 actually printed before the main thread
这里线程2先打印
here thread 2 printed first
线程之间的执行顺序不能保证
execution order between threads is not guaranteed
除非你明确地控制它
unless you explicitly control it
这实际上与进程之间的执行顺序相同
that is actually the same as execution order between processes
正如我们之前讨论过的
and as we discussed in earlier in the module
当然，这是不确定的
of course that can be nondeterministic
所以你必须非常小心
so you have to be very careful
由于这种不确定的执行顺序，会产生bug
and bugs arise because of this nondeterministic execution order
好吧
all right
所以
so
让我们继续
let's roll forward
我们可以再深挖一些吗
can we go lower
我们看过了如何使用pthread创建线程
so we looked at how to create threads using pthread
我们可以（用别的方法）创建线程吗?
can we create threads
显然，pthread是一个库，而不是一个系统调用
obviously pthread is a library it's not a system call
所以底层发生了什么
so what happens under the hood
底层调用了clone系统调用
well under the hood there's a system call called clone
从本质上讲，clone继承自fork
clone is the successor of fork essentially
它是一个更强大、更灵巧的fork
it is fork with a lot more power a lot more finesse
它允许您创建子进程
it allows you to create child processes
可以细致的控制父子进程间共享的资源
and carefully control what is shared between the parent and the child
在这个特殊的案例中
in this specific case
pthread_create就是使用的clone系统调用
this is the clone system call that pthread_create uses
用strace跟踪一下
I will actually strace this
来证明给你看
just to prove it to you
这里是clone
here is this clone
它创建线程2调用的clone
that's the clone for thread 2
这是创建线程1调用的clone
this the clone for thread 1
这些是传递给clone的各种参数
these are the various options passed to clone that
pthread_create用于创建线程
pthread_create uses to create threads
你可以用man查看
you can of course man clone to get all of the information
这些选项的功能
on what all of these different options do
这有很多
and there's quite a lot
我将列举一些常见的，以供参考
I'll go through some common ones just for your information
这是值得知道的好东西
it's good stuff to know
这里最重要的部分是这些flag标志
essentially the important part here is the flags
第一个标志CLONE_VM表示
first flag CLONE_VM means
父子进程共享同一个虚拟内存
we clone the virtual memory space between the parent and child
这和fork不一样
this is different than with fork
使用fork子进程只是获得了父进程内存空间的副本
with fork the child gets a copy of the parent's memory space
使用clone的CLONE_VM参数
with CLONE_VM on clone
表示父子进程将具有相同的内存空间
the parent and child will have the same memory space
如果父进程映射一个内存页
so if the parent maps a page
子进程也可使用这个内存页，反之亦然
it'll be available to the child and vice versa
使用fork则不能
with fork of course that's not the case
CLONE_FS 也一样，但它是针对文件系统的
clone file system is the same but for file system
使用 CLONE_FS
so with CLONE_FS
如果父进程执行chroot，会影响到子进程
if the parent does a chroot it'll affect the child
一个线程会影响其他线程
one thread will affect the other threads
CLONE_FILES是相同的，但是针对文件描述符的
CLONE_FILES is the same but with file descriptor
CLONE_SIGHAND与此相同，但针对信号处理程序
CLONE_SIGHAND is the same but with signal handlers
CLONE_THREAD告诉clone
CLONE_THREAD tells clone that hey
结果将是一个线程
this is going to be a thread
克隆结果是父进程的一个线程
the new child will be a thread of the parent
CLONE_SYSVSEM
clone semaphore information
我一会儿会讲到什么是信号量
I will talk about what semaphores are in a bit here
还有克隆
and cloning
这些选项基本上是记录，额
these options basically do record
这个选项在内存中设置了一个区域
well this option sets up an area in memory
叫线程本地存储 tls，专门用来给这个线程用的
that is storage specifically created for the thread to use is called thread local storage
同一个进程中的不同线程
different threads even in the same process
都有不同的线程本地存储
will have a different thread local storage
这对于存储单个线程内部的全局变量很有用
it's very useful to store kind of global but still thread specific information
这个表示创建线程时要记录线程id
and this basically says when the thread is created store the thread ID
当线程执行完，要从内存中清掉
when the thread is done cleared out from memory
基本是为像pthread之类的clone封装库记录的
its record keeping really for lib pthread and similar libraries that wrap around clone
还有些地址记录了一些信息存储位置
and then some addresses on where to store information
另一个重要的东西是子线程的栈空间
another important thing this child stack
这里是线程的新栈
this is where the new stack for that thread
我提到过线程有自己的栈
I mentioned threads have their own stack
因为他们需要能够执行自己的函数等等
because they need to be able to execute their own functions and so forth
这些都需要栈
all those things grow on the stack
才能互相协作
they're gonna collaborate each others
所以需要一个新的栈
they get a new one
这就是栈所在的位置
and this is where that stack is
如果我们往回看
if we actually jump back and do
查看strace结果
look at our strace
就在这个clone之前
right before this clone
有一个mmap和一个mprotect
there's an mmap and an mprotect
mmap申请了一个栈空间，并返回了它的地址
the mmap maps an extra stack in memory and gets back at this location
这个地址
and that location of course gets passed
至少是这个内存页内的地址
or at least a location within that page
被传给子线程做为栈
gets passed in as the child's stack
并用mprotect置其为栈所需的读写权限
and then that location is mprotected as readable and writeable as a stack should be
所以每个线程都有自己的栈
so each thread gets its own stack created for it
然后用clone分配给线程
and then assigned using that clone system call
非常酷
very cool stuff
clone还可以做其他事情
I'll mention that clone can do other stuff
例如
such as
提供容器所需的功能
starting or providing capabilities that are required for containerization
例如使用CLONE_NEWNS标志
using for example CLONE_NEWNS
它会创建一个新的命名空间
which will create a new name space
这样可以将子进程放到docker容器中
so then you can name space the child into a Docker container for example
好吧
all right
我们讨论的底层接口有些有趣的事
interesting thing while we're talking on the low level
有差异存在于
there are some discrepancies
你熟悉并喜爱的libc函数
between the libc functions you know and love
与他们使用的系统调用之间
and the system calls that they represent
这很重要
and this has to do a lot with threading
这儿举些之后会遇到的例子
right so a couple of examples that we'll run into
比如，用于设置进程安全性的setuid
there is the setting of certain security processes such as setuid
我们看个例子
right so let's take a look at another example here
我又创建了一个使用pthread的文件
I created another file that uses pthread
等一下，这里的done变量多余了
hold on there's a confusing done parameter here that shouldn't be there
这是我们的示例文件
all right so this is our example file
和前面一样创建两个线程
we create two threads as before
这里将第一个线程的UID设置为1000
but here the first thread will set a UID of 1000
好的
right
这有什么用
what this does
虽然Linux单独跟踪
even though Linux individually tracks
我之前说过的
as I said before
每个线程的用户ID、组ID和其他安全属性
the user ID of every thread and the group ID and other security properties
但在POSIX标准中
the standard called the POSIX Standard
即 便携系统。。额
the portable system
忘了
my mind's drawing a blank
你可以在网上查找POSIX代表什么
you can look up what POSIX stands for online
POSIX标准中setuid将设置进程中所有线程的用户ID
the POSIX Standard  basically says that setuid will set the user ID of all threads in a process
如果你使用的是setuid库函数
so if you use setiuid the library function
编译
and we compile this
然后执行
and we execute it
以root权限执行，这样才能使用setuid
let's say as root so that setuid can function
可以看到我们是以root权限执行的
we see the executor as root
但它将所有线程的uid都设置成了1000
but it set all of the threads to UID 1000
如果我们把这个注释掉
um if we instead comment this out
使用原始系统调用
and use the raw syscall
Syscall 105 表示 setuid 的系统调用
syscall 105 is the system call for setuid
当然1000是我们想要设置的ID
and of course 1000 is our ID that we want to set to
编译并运行它
compile that and run it
你看
and you see
只设置了该线程的用户ID
that only the user ID of that thread was set
注意这里的差异
so be careful there's this discrepancy
显然，这可能会带来安全隐患
and it can have security implications obviously
因为某些线程不应该拥有被删除的特权
because certain threads won't have privileges that are dropped
简单说一下
real quick
libc是如何更改所有线程的UID的
how does libc change the UID of all the threads
让我们来看一看
let's take a look
我们再运行一次
so again we run it
它设置进程中所有线程的所有uid
it sets all of the UIDs of all the threads in the process
如果用strace跟踪一下
if you strace it
能看到一些疯狂的东西
there's some crazy stuff
进程中所有线程都触发了SIGRT_1信号
there's this signal SIGRT_1 that gets triggered on every thread in the process
这就是libc在线程之间通信并设置所有用户id的方式
and that's how libc kind of communicates between threads  and sets all of the user IDS
在exit中也存在差异
all right a similar discrepancy actually exists in exit
如果在libc中调用exit
if you call exit in libc
它会调用exit_group系统调用
it'll actually call the exit_group system call
并杀死进程中的所有线程
and kill all of the threads in your process
所有使用CLONE_THREAD标志创建的
anything that was cloned I believe with CLONE_THREAD
但是如果你直接使用exit系统调用
but if you use the exit system call directly
直接调用syscall
again using syscall directly
它只会终止调用者线程
it'll only terminate the caller thread
这是函数返回后的线程终结方式，即使使用的是pthread库
that's how threads terminate in even when you're using pthread when that function returns
好吧
all right
我们讨论一下线程终止
let's talk about thread termination while we're on that topic
线程通常是长时间运行的
threads are often long running
与长时间运行线程的常见通信方式
so common practice for long running threads
是使用全局变量进行通信
is to communicate using global variables
这有一个例子
this is an example
我展示一下该怎样做
let me show you how we might do this
我实现了这个pthread_loop.c
so I implemented this pthread_loop.c
每个线程都在循环中
it's an example that where every thread will loop
每秒输出一次它的线程信息
and every second print out its thread information
主线程将等我按回车键
and the main thread will wait for me to press enter
然后将全局变量done置为1
and set a global variable called done
每个线程都会检查这个变量
that every thread is checking
这是一种常见的设计
this is a common design
也许是反？？
maybe anti-pan
但是是处理线程的一种常见方式
but a common way that threads are handled
最起码是在多线程初学者的代码中
in definitely you know the sort of beginner threading code
他们会持续运行，直到某个全局状态让他们结束
they'll keep running until some global state says that they are done
这个全局状态能被其他线程访问
and this global state can be touched by other threads
让我给你看看这是什么样子
let me show you what this looks like
好吧
all right
我们编译
we compiled it
这个一直在运行
this keeps running
然后当我按回车键
and then when I hit enter
他们结束了
boom they're done
好的
all right
现在有趣的是
now the interesting thing here
在这里，只有一个线程会修改done变量
is that in this case just one thread is touching this done variable
但可以想象如果多个线程共享一个全局状态
but you can imagine if multiple threads are sharing a global state
而且他们的调度执行顺序是不确定的
and multiple threads whose execution scheduling is nondeterministic
他们都会读写这个全局变量
are reading from and writing to that global state
那就会遇到和文件系统案例非常相似的问题
then you have a very similar problem to the file system case
你创建了一个共享资源
you just created a shared resource
又有多个同步不良的进程或线程
that multiple badly synchronized processes essentially or threads in this case
多个进线程都可以随时修改这些共享资源
which are basically processes that share a bunch of resources can touch all at once
接下来我们将研究如何滥用这一点
of course next we look into how this can be abused